<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to the rector's libel, or, The Bishop's case truly stated shewing, I. that the rector has stated the case disingeniously [sic], II. that the rubrick and canons which he quotes ... do manifestly turn to his own condemnation, III. that the three queries ...  upon which he builds the whole resolution, are (modestly speaking) impertinently put, and falsly, or impertinently resolv'd.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25619</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3440</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41255</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31354692</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31354692</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110231</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25619)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110231)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1734:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to the rector's libel, or, The Bishop's case truly stated shewing, I. that the rector has stated the case disingeniously [sic], II. that the rubrick and canons which he quotes ... do manifestly turn to his own condemnation, III. that the three queries ...  upon which he builds the whole resolution, are (modestly speaking) impertinently put, and falsly, or impertinently resolv'd.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Wilde ... and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cashel Diocesan Library, Cashel, Ireland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Discipline.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Rector of Dr---r's case concerning the power of suspension from the sacrament stated.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110231:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110231:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO THE RECTOR'S LIBEL OR, THE BISHOP'S CASE TRULY STATED. SHEWING
<list>
                  <item>I. That the Rector has Stated the CASE diſingeniouſly.</item>
                  <item>II. That the Rubrick and Canons which he quotes in his Juſtification do maniſeſtly turn to his own Condemnation.</item>
                  <item>III. That the Three Queries (1. <hi>Whether a Rector hath Power to Suſpend any of the Pariſhioners committed to his Charge, from a Temporary Reception of the Sacrament? And in what Caſes he may exerciſe that Power.</hi> 2. <hi>What is the Biſhops Office in ſuch a Caſe? And whether he may reſtore ſuch Perſons ſo Suſpended, without a Judicial Cognizance of the Crime ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected.</hi> 3. <hi>Whether in ſuch a Caſe the Biſhop may regularly command the Rector, and whether ſuch commands are obliging?</hi>) Upon which he builds the whole Reſolution, are (modeſtly ſpeaking) impertinently put, and falſly, or impertinently Reſolv'd.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Revileſt thou Gods High Prieſt.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Act. 23.40.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Siquis Clericus Epiſcopum contumelia affecerit deponitor.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Apoſ. Can. 54.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>DUBLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Richard Wilde</hi> in <hi>Skinner-Row,</hi> and are to be Sold at his Shop in <hi>Cork Change,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110231:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110231:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE RECTOR'S LIBEL, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE other day I met with, and read a Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, Intituled, <hi>The Rectors Caſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Power of Suſpenſion from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> &amp;c. which ſent me (in Indignation againſt ſo falſe and ſcandalous a Libel) to my Study, where in a very little time, the Rectors Weakneſs rather than my own Skill, enabled me to give the following Anſwer, which ſhews,
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>That the Rector has ſtated the Caſe diſingeniouſly.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>That the Rubrick and Canons which he quotes in his Juſtification, do manifeſtly turn to his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>That the Three Queries upon which he Builds the whole Reſolution, are (modeſtly ſpeaking) imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently put, and falſly, or impertinently reſolv'd.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:110231:3"/>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>That the Rector has Stated the Caſe diſingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly</hi>) will in part appear from the plain matter of Fact here impartially related. In the year 1693. <hi>April</hi> 14. being <hi>Good Friday,</hi> The Rector ſent a Letter to Mr. <hi>M. S.</hi> Steward to the Biſhop, and another Letter to the ſame purpoſe to Mr. <hi>T. N.</hi> the Biſhops Gentleman, wherein the Rector ſaid, <hi>He thought himſelf by Conſcience as well as Law, Obliged to Admoniſh the aforeſaid Gentlemen, being his Pariſhioners, not to approach the Holy Table the Sunday following, for that they were <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nqualify'd to receive the Holy Sacrament: Becauſe, as he was told by ſome, (naming no body) That they were concerned in a Conſpiracy againſt his Life.</hi> Upon theſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the two Gentlemen, tho' wholly innocent, and declaring their Charity with the Rector and all the World, did in ſubmiſſion forbear the Sacrament at that time, leſt the Rector might, by publickly, and, it may be, indecently repelling them, give oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of Scandal: But a year clapſing, and the Rector during all that time, neither by Word nor Writing, before the Solemnities of Whitſuntide or Chriſtmas, nor any other time again Admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid Gentlemen, nor Proſecuting, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the heavy Charge of their being concerned in a Conſpiracy againſt his Life; therefore the ſaid Centlemen on Eaſter Sunday 1694. came up Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110231:3"/>to the Rails (and were not brought in by the Biſhop <hi>vi &amp; armis,</hi> as the Rector maliciouſly and falſly ſuggeſts <hi>Pag.</hi> 13.) there to receive with other Communicants in the Cathedral Church of the Dioceſs, where the Biſhop in Perſon Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered, and the Rector Aſſiſted: But juſt as the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop was about to begin the Service at the Altar, the Rector ſtep'd to the two Gentlemen, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad them the Sacrament; the Biſhop obſerving the ſame, ſpake to the Rector not to trouble himſelf, or words to that purpoſe; and after when the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments came to be diſtributed, the Biſhop Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtered the Bread to his two Servants, as he did to the other Communicants; but the Rector giving the Cup to the reſt willfully omitted the aforeſaid Gentlemen, and paſſing them by, placed the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice upon the Table, which the Biſhop obſerving, commanded the Rector to give them the Cup; but the Rector reply'd poſitively and paſſionately that he would not, adding theſe Words; <hi>Let it be between me and God;</hi> upon which the Biſhop, without a word more, or ſhewing any concern; gave them the Cup. Now obſerve, that in the Rector's State of the caſe, there is
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>No Notice taken of the Biſhop's Adminiſtering the Sacrament in his own Cathedral.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:110231:4"/>
                     <item>2. <hi>The Rector is there ſaid actually to have Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended the two Gentlemen; whereas his own Letters to them ſay only he thought himſelf obliged to Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them, but not a word of actually Suſpending them.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>The Reaſon he gives, is their Notorious, Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Contrivances and practices againſt himſelf, for, as 'tis worded in one of his own Letters, againſt his Life; whereas in the ſame Letter he owns it was but a hear-ſay without mention of any Proof or Author.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>He ſays he acquainted the Biſhop herewith: 'Tis true he wrote a moſt impudent and ſcandalous Letter to the Biſhop, falſly charging both him and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants with Hainous things, but all General, without deſcending to particulars then, or ever offering to prove any ſince.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>He ſays the Biſhop interpos'd paſſionately for his Servants, than which nothing can be more falſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. <hi>He modeſtly ſays, He declin'd giving them the Cup; whereas he flatly and paſſionately refuſed it, and like Chriſt's Crucifiers, imprecated the Guilt thereof upon himſelf.— I come now to ſhew</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>II. That the Rubrick and Canons which the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor quotes in his Juſtification, do manifeſtly turn to his own Condemnation.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Rubrick;</hi> the firſt Paragraph whereof ſays, <hi>That they who intend to partake, ſhould ſignifie their Names at leaſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110231:4"/>ſome time the day before;</hi> which as the Rector truly urges, <hi>Pag.</hi> 20. was no doubt ſo Ordained, That the Rector might know who intended to Communicate, and that accordingly he might Inſtruct, Comfort, Counſel, Reprove or Abſolve, as there was Cauſe, as 'tis ſaid, or imply'd in the latter end of the firſt Exhortation to the Communion. But did the ſaid Rector ever in his Life, uſe the Pariſh to, or acquaint the people with this Rubrick and Intent thereof? Or did he, as by the 19th Canon he was obliged, give Warning the Afternoon before, by tolling of a Bell, or any other way, for ſcrupulous perſons to repair to him for Comfort? Or did he, purſuant to his Admonition to the two Gentlemen, either come to them, or ſend for them, to Examine them ſeriouſly as to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Crimes, and their obſtinacy in them, or ſorrow for them, or innocency of them? Did he any time in the year following thus acquit himſelf? Surely this was his Duty, and far more Decent and leſs Offenſive, than to ſurprize them at the Rails a year after his firſt and only Admonition, which he ſeemed to give them in a heat.</p>
               <p>As to the ſecond Paragraph of the Rubrick; ſo far were the Gentlemen from being obnoxious to it, that they bear infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a better Character for their Lives and peaceable Behaviour in the whole Countrey, than the Rector himſelf, which I am ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for? but yet ſo ſure of, that we will venture the whole iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue upon that point; and in the mean time can produce under the Church-Wardens hands of the Pariſh, a Preſentment made againſt the Rector, among other things, for his repelling the ſaid Gentlemen, as giving offence to many; foraſmuch as they are perſons (as 'tis worded in the body of the preſentment) of good Life and Converſation, not reputed Notorious or Scandalous Livers, or any way vitiouſly inclin'd, nor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious among their Neighbours, or Offenſive to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. Now this is ſuch a Character, and upon Oath too, as the Rector is far from deſerving; nor can he procure ſuch
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110231:5"/>a Teſtimony from the Hands of his beſt Friends in the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, unleſs they be notoriouſly Scandalous, who do not value or Eſteem their Reputation.</p>
               <p>The Third Paragraph is likewiſe Anſwer'd under the ſaid Church Wardens Hands, who declare the two Gentlemen, neither to be Contentious, nor any wiſe offenſive to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; and conſequently there was no neceſſity of their making ſatisfaction, no ſcandal being given by them, nor ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt them by any perſon but the Rector himſelf: But on the contrary, it is Notorious, That the Rector is Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and Litigious, and that as the Rubrick words it, <hi>He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues ſtill in his frowardneſs,</hi> that he has been of a long time and ſtill is, involv'd in Law-Suits with his Neighbours; that he has given, and does ſtill give Scandal and Offence to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by diſaffected Words and Actions, to his Biſhop by moſt Undutiful and Scurrilous ones; (for Which we refer to the Viſitors and Proceedings in the late Triennial Viſitation) and to the whole Pariſh and Neighbourhood, by his Moroſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Negligence in his Office: For ſo the Church-War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens in the aforeſaid Preſentment have Authentically Tax'd him, as with horrible neglect of his Duty, to the great Injury and Diſhonour of our Church; ſo alſo (which is moſt to the matter in hand) with Peeviſhneſs and Contentiouſneſs of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and addictedneſs to Strife and Law-Suits; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if in any thing the Biſhop was blame-worthy; 'twas in admitting the Rector to the Sacrament, before that he, who had given ſuch Offence, had made a ſuitable ſatisfaction. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as to the two Canons, which the Rector quotes (tho' one would have ſerv'd, being Verbatim the ſame in the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Edition) 'tis evident from what has been ſaid, that 'tis the Rector who has malitiouſly contended with his Neighbours, and not Mr. <hi>M. S.</hi> who had no Suit, nor any difference with any body; nor Mr. <hi>T. N.</hi> who only had a Suit at Law with the Rector himſelf which rais'd his Spleen. 'Tis the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110231:5"/>Rector offended the Congregation; and even at that they deter'd many worthy perſons from that comfortable Feaſt. As for inſtance, Sir <hi>J. M.</hi> who declar'd that he would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Sacrament that <hi>Eaſter,</hi> but that he could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear taking Offence at the Rector, upon the ſcore of his Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, Railing Sermons continually about that time; and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, for that the Rector declar'd himſelf out of Charity with Mr. A. B. and when the ſaid Mr. A. B. ask'd the Rector whether he was not to give and Receive the Sacrament the Sunday following, the Rector anſwered he was, but yet was not in Charity with him: Likewiſe Mr. <hi>T. D.</hi> told the Church-Wardens, That he would have Receiv'd the Sacrament that <hi>Eaſter</hi> Sunday, if any Miniſter but the Rector had Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciated; but was afraid the Rector would have refus'd him the Sacrament, or have publickly Affronted him: The very ſame thing likewiſe Captain <hi>R. J.</hi> declar'd, as by the ſaid Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may appear. Now let the Rector prove, that ever ſo much offence, or indeed any Offence at all, was given to the Congregation by either Mr. <hi>M. S.</hi> or Mr. <hi>T. N.</hi> And alſo let any Man judg whether the Rubrick and Canons which the Rector has quoted in Order to juſtifie himſelf, do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn him; and if ſo, then he is condemn'd, as himſelf well obſerves, <hi>Page</hi> 5th, by the Judgments of the Convocations and Parliaments of both Kingdoms.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>III. The next thing I have, to prove is, That the three Queries, upon which the Rector builds the whole Reſolution, are (modeſtly ſpeaking) impertinently put, and falſly, or impertinently Reſolv'd.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Impertinently put,</hi> for that no Man denies; Firſt, That the Rector of a private Pariſh is preſum'd ordinarily to be the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110231:6"/>beſt acquainted with the Qualifications of his Pariſhioners, and may repel from the Sacrament for a time, any of them who is a notorious ill Liver, or an open Malitious Contender with his Neighbours. And as to the Second Query, 'tis grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that upon regular information to the Biſhop, he is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt ſuch a Notorious Sinner, in caſe he continues ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, according to the Canon. And as to the Third, during ſuch the obſtinacy of the aforeſaid Offender, the Biſhop ought not to command the Rector to Adminiſter him the Sacrament: So that, it's plain the Queries were Impertinently put.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the ſaid Queries are alſo falſly, or impertinently Reſolv'd by the Rector, will alſo appear by the following Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations.</p>
               <p>As to the firſt Query, the Rector, <hi>Pag.</hi> 6. quotes Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> for affirming that by the Words, <hi>Whoſe Sins thou doſt forgive, they are forgiven, and whoſe Sins thou doſt retain, they are retained,</hi> is meant the Power of Binding and Looſing, and that this is no other than the Power of admitting to, and Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending from the Sacrament. Now that this is a great part of the ſaid Power, the Dr. and we all grant; but we cannot grant it to be the whole Power given in thoſe Words, till the Rector does furniſh us with ſome other Texts, whereupon to found the Power of that ordinary Abſolution, which we dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pronounce, both publickly in Church, and privately to ſick Perſons and Penitents, when there is no Celebration of the Sacrament. To my knowledg the great <hi>Andrews</hi> chooſes thoſe very Words for his Text, St. <hi>Jo.</hi> 20.23. when in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Preached at <hi>Whitehal,</hi> he undertakes to prove this Power of Abſolution: The Rector likewiſe there affirms, that he has Power to Suſpend any perſon from the Sacrament, that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to him unqualify'd. Now obſerve Dr. <hi>Hammond Prac. Cat. p.</hi> 394. ſays, <hi>That Chriſt himſelf Adminiſtered the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to</hi> Judas, <hi>tho he knew his heart to be full of Villany; and that therefore 'tis lawful to admit Sinners to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:110231:6"/>'Tis true, he deſires, this to be underſtood warily, and owns that Governours of the Church may inflict their Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures upon Willful, Scandalous Sinners, and withdraw the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament by way of Diſcipline, and in Charity to their Souls; but yet in caſe the ſaid Offenders be not actually under the Church Cenſures, and do preſs for the Sacrament; the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter may Communicate with them at the Offenders own Peril; from which it appears, that in caſe our two Gentlemen were Scandalous Sinners; yet they being under no Eccleſiaſtical Cenſure and preſſing for the Sacrament, it had been no Sin in the Rector to have admitted them: And further, that they muſt have been wilful, Scandalous Sinners, otherwiſe the Rector had no Right to repel them: And indeed, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſon ſo to be repell'd, muſt be an open, and Notorious ill-Liver, or an open Contender, who gives Offence to the Congregation; and conſequently whoſe unqualifiedneſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to others, as well as to the Rector himſelf, both the Rubricks and Canons affirm: And ſo do the Ancient Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts. <hi>Reccatoribus notoriis Euchariſtia non eſt Adminiſtranda;</hi> but then is added what Notoriety is required; <hi>Notorium Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorem dici; qui manifeſtus eſt vel per ſententiam, vel per con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſionem factam in judicio, out per evidentiam rei, quae nulia tergiverſatione celari poteſt;</hi> Aug. Bar. Cap. 20 n. 20.21. So that it muſt not be the ſurmiſe of the Rector himſelf, or a bare hear-ſay; but ſuch an immorality, as is notorions by a ſentence, or Legal Confeſſion, or Evidence of Fact, ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly known, as cannot be conceal'd; otherwiſe, neither the Rector nor Biſhop ought to repel. Now let the Rector prove the two Gentlemen thus Notorious, if he can. Oh, but, ſays the Rector, <hi>Pag.</hi> 7. <hi>'Tis left to my own diſcretive judgment whom to Suſpend:</hi> 'Tis true, the Ruorick ſeems to make him Judge for fourteen days, but not for the whole year, as it was in our Caſe: Now, either the Rector did not legally inform the Biſhop within the fourteen days, and then
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110231:7"/>himſelf Tranſgreſſed the Rubrick; or if he did, then not the Rector, but the Biſhop, after ſuch Information given, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Judge, and may Puniſh, or Pardon, as he ſees Cauſe. And further obſerve (as the Rector himſelf well Objects, and could not Anſwer) that the Rector Suſpended them for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and Injuries and Contrivances againſt himſelf; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought not to be a Judge in his own Cauſe; to which I add, That firſt, <hi>non conſtat,</hi> no ſuch Malice in the two Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen is prov'd; <hi>Et quilibet preſumitur bonus, donec probatur in contrarium.</hi> Next, That tho' in the Caſe of Malice or Contention between two Pariſhioners, the Miniſter is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd an allowable Judge, yet not ſo, where himſelf is a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: And laſtly, whereas the Rector Anſwers, that this muſt be allow'd in this caſe; becauſe there is no third perſon to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervene; I ſay, <hi>This is a miſtake;</hi> for the Biſhop is a proper perſon to intervene in the aforeſaid Caſe. The 9th <hi>Can. Con. Caſe.</hi> makes the Biſhop the proper Judge of Clergy-Men; and our Rubrick makes him proper Judge over the people, to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them according to the Canon: And indeed he being the common Paſtor of his whole Dioceſs, (<hi>Nam ipſi commiſſus eſt Dei populus, &amp; pro animabus eorum ipſe redditurus eſt ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem:</hi> Apoſ. Can. 40.) And ſeeing the Rectors in their Pariſhes are but his ſubſtitutes over the people; none can ſo properly mediate in a difference between his ſubſtitute and people, as the common Ruler, who has equally an Authority and Care over both.</p>
               <p n="2">2 All that is material under his Second Query, is, that the Biſhop was negligent of his Duty in not cenſuring the Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended perſons; but inſtead thereof admitting them to the Sacrament; <hi>Pag.</hi> 12. And Secondly, That the Biſhop had not the Right of Adminiſtering the Sacrament there. As to the firſt, I ſay, 'Tis true, that upon Information given to a Biſhop by the Rector, who Suſpends a Notorious Offender from the Sacrament; the Biſhop is to proceed againſt ſuch
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110231:7"/>Notorious Perſon according to the Canon; but 'tis with this Proviſo, that ſuch notorious perſon perſiſt obſtinately in his Fault, not otherwiſe; for ſo the Rector owns, <hi>Pag.</hi> 8.9.10. If more gentle means prove effectual to reclaim ſuch Sinners, if friendly Admonition do the Work, then ſeverity is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, and the Biſhop may accept of their preſent Sorrow, and Promiſes of future Amendment. And all this for ought the Rector knew, might have been done in the preſent Caſe. Oh, but, ſays the Rector, <hi>When the Offence is an Injuſtice, and an Injury to a Neighbour, there Reſtitution; and when a Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal is given to the Congregation, there Publick Satisfaction is required; at leaſt the Offender muſt be made to declare himſelf ready ſo to ſatisfie.</hi> All this is granted, but then there is nothing of this in the preſent Caſe; for the Gentlemen were never known to be Men of either Scandalous, or Malicious Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or Practices; but as has been ſaid, <hi>Of a far better Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation than the Rector.</hi> That, <hi>They Conſpired againſt his Life,</hi> is an Allegation founded upon a hear-ſay, as in the aforementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Letters, under his Hand himſelf does own: And no body living of tolerable Credit, will ſay, or believe they are ſuch perſons as he has repreſented them; or if they were, why did not the Rector make it appear before the Biſhop, being bound to juſtifie what he did, and to proſecute them for what he laid to their Charge? Or, Why did he not proceed againſt them at Common-Law, in caſe he thought the Biſhop would be too favourable? But, he letting near a whole year paſs, without any ſuch Animadverſion, or even a ſecond Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and they on their part having Solemnly declared to the Biſhop, and to others of the Clergy of the beſt Dignity in the Dioceſs, that they had no perſonal prejudice to the Rector, more than a diſlike to him upon the ſcore of his being an Ill and Diſaffected Man, and that they were in Charity with him and all the World; and upon this ſtock of Innocency and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity deſiring the benefit of the Sacrament: Let any Man judg,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110231:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>whether the Biſhop had moſt reaſon to regard theſe Solemn Aſſeverations of his two Servants, whom he perſonally knew to be Men of Integrity, or to regard the unwarrantable heat, and Malicious and groundleſs Allegation of the Rector, who is known by all to be an Obſtinate, ſelf-will'd, and ill-natur'd Man. But,</p>
               <p>Secondly, ſays the Rector, <hi>The Biſhop had no Authority to Adminiſter the Sacrament there and therefore it was an Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of my Right.</hi> To this, Firſt, That the Biſhop has Power to Adminiſter the Sacrament in Vertue of his Order, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be the ſame with that of Prieſt, or a Superiour; I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Rector is not ſo utterly beſide himſelf as to deny. But, <hi>Fruſtra eſt potentia quae non reducitur in actum:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Power muſt be Executed ſomewhere; and if the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop may Adminſter any where, it muſt be, either in Cathedral and Collegiate, or in Pariſh Churches: No, ſays the Rector, <hi>in neither. For though the 24th Engliſh Canon ſeems to allow the Biſhop ſometimes in Cathedrals, where there are no Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Cures, to Adminiſter; yet our Rubrick, which is a far better Authority, gives the Right of Conſecration in Cathedrals to the Prebendaries, and in Pariſh Churches to the Rector or Vicar, and this excluſive of the Biſhop; becauſe 'tis only reſerv'd for him to pronounce the Abſolution, and give the Bleſſing,</hi> Pag. 13. Never was there ſuch a Meſs of Ignorance and Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance: For Biſhops have the Original Power of Conſecration, and the Presbiters have it by delegation from them: The Presbiters have the Power to Conſecrate, <hi>in actu ſignato,</hi> upon the ſcore of their Ordination, which they had from the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; and likewiſe they have the exerciſe of this Power from the Biſhop, by Vertue of their Inſtitution; whereby a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Congregation is given them to Adminiſter to: But ſurely when a Biſhop impowers another, he does not diveſt himſelf. No, this he cannot do, if he would, this Power being Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to his Office by Divine Inſtitution: Nay, in the firſt Ages
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110231:8"/>of the Church, e're Presbyters had their appropriated Pariſhes, we find that the Presbyters could not Conſecrate without the Biſhop's Licence, tho he were abſent: So St <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who lived <hi>anno</hi> 101. ſays in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Smyrnaans, Let no Man do any thing of what belongs to the Church, without the Biſhops leave,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Neither Baptiſe, nor offer Sacrifice, but let that Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt be look'd upon as firm and good, which is either offer'd by the Biſhop, or by him whom the Biſhop ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. And even after Congregations were Aſſign'd as proper Cures to Presbyters, and the Biſhops had given them an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Licence once for all to Conſecrate, yet notwithſtanding, when the Biſhop was perſonally preſent, they did not Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter without a new leave; ſo St. <hi>Leo</hi> in 86th Epiſtle to the Biſhops of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France, Sed ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> coram Epiſcopo licet Presbyteris introire Baptiſterium,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Nec eo preſente, niſi jubente, Sacramentum Corporis &amp; Sanguinis Chriſti conficere:</hi> i. e. It is not lawful for Presbyters to enter into the Baptiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor to Conſecrate the Sacrament of Chriſts Body and Blood, if the Biſhop be preſent, without his Command: And ſo ſays, <hi>Con. Carth.</hi> 2. <hi>Can.</hi> 9. <hi>Quiſquis Praesbiter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente &amp; inconſulto Epiſcopo agenda in quolibet loco voluerit ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrare, itſe honori ſuo contrarius exiſtit:</hi> If any Presbyter without leave of the Biſhop, he being preſent, ſhall Celebrate the Sacrament, be the place what it will (Cathedral or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church) is an Enemy to the Biſhops Dignity: And <hi>Con. Sen.</hi> ſeems to explain the matter, both as to time and place, <hi>Epiſcopi in ſuis Diaeceſſibus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in Feſtivitatibus Solemnibus per ſe in Eccleſiis ſuis celebrent:</hi> i. e. Biſhops in their Dioceſſes ſhall in their own Perſons (not by their Prebendaries) celebrate the Sacrament upon the ſolemn Feſtivals in their Churches. To which the 24th Engliſh Canon almoſt literally agrees. And 'tis, no doubt, the <hi>Biſhop's</hi> Authority extends through his whoſe Dioceſs, and to every Church therein, the Charge and Care where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110231:9"/>is committed to him, which he can never free himſelf from; and though he has committed part of it to others, becauſe he cannot be preſent every where, yet where he is preſent, the Rector or Vicar being but his Subſtitute, are, if he pleaſe to officiate, <hi>pro tunc</hi> ſuperſeded; <hi>In proeſentia majoris ceſſat poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia minoris.</hi> But however this be, 'tis certain that of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral, as <hi>Rebuff.</hi> ſays, <hi>(Epiſcopus eſt propriè &amp; immediatè Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochus)</hi> the Biſhop is the proper and immediate Minſter. And ſo the 24th Engliſh Canon, chiefly intitles him to the Right of Adminiſtring there, though not excluſive of the Dignitaries: And thus 'tis practiſed and allow'd all over <hi>England</hi> no body (I believe) in that whole Nation ever knowing that it was refus'd to the Biſhop, or thought an Uſurpation in him to Adminiſter the Sacrament in his Cathedral.</p>
               <p>Again, the Rector Abuſes the Rubrick; 'tis true, it ſays, <hi>That the Miniſter</hi> (not mentioning what Order) <hi>ſhall firſt Receive the Communion in both kinds himſelf, and then proceed to deliver the ſame to the Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons in like manner</hi> (if any be preſent) <hi>and after that to the People:</hi> The true meaning whereof muſt be this, that he who Adminiſters the Sacrament, ſhall obſerve this Order in the diſtribution of the Elements; Firſt, to Adminiſter to the Clergy according to their Order; as firſt to Biſhops, Whether of other Dioceſſes, that may happen to be preſent on that occaſion, or the Biſhop of the Dioceſs, who in eaſe to his Age or Indiſpoſition, may admit the Prieſt to perform the Office: Next them to Prieſts, then to the Deacons, and after to the Laity. And, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Order, nor my ſenſe of it are New, I refer you, for ſome thing much like this, to the great Council of <hi>Nice, Can.</hi> 14. <hi>Pervenit ad Sanctum Concilium, quod in locis quibuſ: dam &amp; Civitatibus, Praesbyteris Sacramenta Diaconi porrigant; hoc ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> regula, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> conſuetudo tradidit, ut hi qui offerende Sacrificii non habeat poteſtatem, his qui offerant Corpus Chriſti porrigant, ſed &amp; illud immotuit, quod quidam Diaconi etiam
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110231:9"/>aute Epiſcopum Sacramentà ſumunt; haec ergo omnia amputen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; accipiant ſecundum Ordinem, poſt Presbyteros ab Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copo vel a Praesbytero, Sacram Communionem.</hi> Which implies, That the Biſhop may Adminiſter, and that the Clergy ought to Receive according to their Order.</p>
               <p>Again, 'tis to be conſider'd in the preſent Caſe, that the two Suſpended perſons (as the Rector calls them) were the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops chief Domeſticks. Now ſurely, no Rector is preſuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to know his Pariſhioners Qualifications better than a Biſhop may be allow'd to know the fitneſs, or unfitneſs of his Servants; it being one Qualification of a Biſhop, that he know well, and govern well his own Houſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. Oh, but, ſays the Rector, <hi>Thoſe Servants were my Pariſhioners, and therefore I had the Right to Adminiſter to them, and not the Biſhop.</hi> This is a hard Caſe, That Biſhops muſt neither Adminiſter in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrals, nor Pariſh Churches, to the Inhabitants of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſs at large, nor even to thoſe of his own Family. But let this be the Biſhop's Comfort, whatever the Rector ſays, others know, that Biſhops may Adminiſter to any, or all the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; and ſo particularly ſays <hi>Aug. Bar. pag.</hi> 308. <hi>n.</hi> 12. <hi>Quem libet poſſe, otium invito Parocho, Epiſcopum adire pro Sacramento ſuſcipiendo, cum illi principaliter commiſſa ſit Cura omnium animarum ſuae Dioceſios,</hi> i. e. any Man may, whether his Miniſter will or no, repair to the Biſhop to Receive the Sacrament, becauſe chiefly to him is committed the Care of all the Souls in his Dioceſs.</p>
               <p>From the whole then, I think 'tis plain the Biſhop had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Authority, and Good Reaſon to Adminiſter the Bleſſed Sacrament, eſpecially in his own Cathedral, and chiefly to his own Servants, of whoſe fitneſs he was aſſur'd, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had no Cauſe to proceed againſt them, according to the Canon, as againſt Notorious, Scandalous, Obſtinate Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:110231:10"/>
               <p>Thirdly, The Third Query is, <hi>Whether in ſuch Caſe the Biſhop may regularly command the Rector, and ſuch Commands are obliging?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moſt of what the Rector ſays on this Query, no body needs diſprove, as that great Care ought to be taken of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming Sinners, and fitting perſons for the Holy Sacrament, and of preventing Scandalous Communicants: And therefore let the Biſhop Anſwer for admitting the Rector; for as the matter appears to me upon the whole from the good Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter the two Gentlemen bear in their Country, and the ill one the Rector has; and from his Rude and Paſſionate De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment towards the Biſhop himſelf, and his Servants, before, at, and ſince that Holy Sacrament, the Rector is the only unqualify'd perſon; who diſcover'd his Malice in the very Celebration of thoſe Myſteries, which are a Contradiction to every thing that is not real Love and Charity.</p>
               <p>What more is worthy our Obſervation upon this Query, may be comprehended in theſe three Things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>I. That the Rector, <hi>pag.</hi> 21, ſavs, <hi>Epiſcopacy is not a diſtinct Order from Presbytery, but only the ſuperaddition of a New Office to it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>That the Power of Biſhops is only fraternal, to Admoniſh, but not to Command; at moſt they had but a Negative Voice before the Popiſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>That the Oath of Canonical Obedience is alſo a Relick of Popery, and that the impoſition of it is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, and the Rectors taking of it uncertain,</hi> pag. 18.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That Epiſcopacy is not a diſtinct Ordeo from Presbytery,</hi> &amp;c. It cannot be expected I ſhould here enter into this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, and ſhew you all the Authorities from Scripture, Antiquity, and the conſent of all Chriſtian Churches for 1500 years, but a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ll that I ſhall urge, <hi>ad hominem,</hi> is to ſhew
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110231:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>how the Rector has by this Poſition expos'd his own baſeneſs. Know then, he has twice at his Ordinations ſubſcrib'd to the 4th Canon, which maintains the three Orders of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons; and three or four times more ſubſcrib'd it at his admiſſion to Benefices; and has as often ſubſcrib'd the 39 Articles, whereof the 36th maintains the ſaid Orders; and has declar'd the ſame (I believe) ten times, in reading his Aſſent and Conſent to all things contain'd in the Book of Common-Prayer, and Adminiſtration of Sacraments, and the manner of making, Ordaining and Conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons; and has in his late very Pamphlet own'd and declar'd the Rubrick of the ſaid Book, to have the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Authority, that Statute Law can give it: Yet this Rubrick before the form of Ordination, runs thus; <q rend="inline">It is evident unto all Men diligently reading the Holy Scriptures, and Ancient Fathers, that from the Apoſtles time, there have been theſe Orders of Miniſters in the Church, Biſhops, Prieſts and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Now that any Man profeſſing himſelf a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England</hi> for at leaſt 20 years, and ſtill from time to time declaring, ſubſcribing, and owning the three Orders, ſhould give the contrary under his Hand, and Print it to Eternize his Villany, and to render himſelf obnoxious to the Penalties of the Laws both Canon and Statute, is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration that he is Mad, and fit for <hi>Bedlam.</hi> Let him not think to come off with his owning Epiſcopacy to be a Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Office, for the Rubrick calls them expreſly three Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and the Canon and Articles muſt accordingly be ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and that Power of Ordination appropriated to Biſhops, ſhows it to be an Order, ſince it is the Power that makes the Order, and manifeſts it unto us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Rector ſays, <hi>That the Power of Biſhops is only Fraternal, to Admoniſh, but not to Command; at moſt they had but a Negative Voice before the Popiſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:110231:11"/>
               <p>'Tis true, Biſhops and Prieſts are Brethren, and ſhould treat one another as ſuch, and not be Tyrannical; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two there is a Medium, and an allow'd Power in Biſhops over Presbyters, and all this before the Popiſh U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation. So Dr. <hi>Cave, prim. Chriſt. par.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. ſays, <hi>It was not the buſineſs of the Biſhops barely to preſide in the Aſſemblies of the Clergy; but to call them to Account, and Suſpend them if they deſerv'd it.</hi> And if <hi>Baronius</hi> may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to ſpeak, he tell us, <hi>ad annum</hi> 57 <hi>&amp;</hi> 319 <hi>That the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciary Power of Biſhops over Clergy and Laity was Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted of God, Exercis'd by the Holy Fathers, and confirm'd by the Emperors.</hi> And indeed <hi>Euſebius</hi> in the Life of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> hints the ſame, <hi>Cap.</hi> 27. which <hi>Valeſius</hi> refers to a Law of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> extant in the cloſe of the <hi>Theodoſian Code.</hi> But (methinks) the Rectors own Negative inſtance from <hi>Ignatius, That nothing be done without the Biſhop,</hi> implies an Affirmative, <hi>That every thing be done by his Direction and Command.</hi> And ſo doth the <hi>Apoſ. Can.</hi> 40. <hi>Praesbyteri &amp; Diaconi praeter E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopum nihil pertentent.</hi> And ſometimes in ſome Caſes, the Clergy are expreſly ſaid to be under the Biſhops Command. For inſtance, <hi>Con. Laod. Can.</hi> 42. <hi>No Miniſter of Gods Altar, nor any Clergy-Man muſt take a Journey, but</hi> per juſſionem, <hi>by the Command of his Biſhop: Nor muſt they, diſreſpecting the Biſhop, make Conventicles apart, or ſet up Altars, upon pain if Depoſition. Apoſ. Can.</hi> 32. and ſo <hi>Con. Gang. Can.</hi> 6. It were endleſs to quote Authorities of Authentick Canons and Fathers to the ſame purpoſe. As for us, our own Canons, particularly the 71ſt, ſufficiently impowers the Biſhop to Suſpend, Deprive, or Depoſe the Inferiour Clergy upon juſt Cauſes; and ſo does the Statute in <hi>England,</hi> 1 <hi>Eliz. Cap.</hi> 2. make every Spiritual perſon, Dignitary or Parſon, Viſitable by the Biſhop or Ordinary; who thereby is Authoriz'd to enquire into and puniſh their Faults, by Admonition, Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, Sequeſtration, or Deprivation.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:110231:11"/>
               <p n="3">3. The Rector ſays, <hi>That the Oath of Canonical Obedience is alſo a Relick of Popery, and that the Impoſition of it is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, and the Rector's taking of it uncertain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To theſe things, I ſay; Firſt, That Obedience is due, and has been always from Presbyters to Biſhops, as the quotations in the former Paragraph do prove: For Command and Obey being Relatives, whatever proves the one, proves the other alſo: But beſide the 18th <hi>Can.</hi> of the <hi>Con. Arl.</hi> 1. held ten or twelve years before the <hi>Nic.</hi> ſays, <hi>The Deacons muſt not take upon them on their own Accounts, but let Honour be reſerv'd to the Presbyters; and that Presbyters likewiſe do nothing, but</hi> conſcientio Epiſcopi, <hi>by the Privity and Conſent of the Biſhop;</hi> in which is ſufficiently imply'd the great Deference, Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Obedience, which the Inferiour Orders owe to their reſpective Superiours. And the Counſel of <hi>Calc. Can.</hi> 8. firſt ſetting forth the Biſhops Authority over the Clergy in their Pariſhes, &amp;c. does then enjoyn their Submiſſion and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>At ſi noluerint ſubjacere,</hi> in caſe they refuſe ſo to O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, let them be Puniſh'd Canonically. And <hi>Con. Agath. Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Let the contumacious Clergy be Corrected and Puniſh'd by their Biſhops;</hi> which plainly proves the Power of the one, and the Obedience of the other. The like ſaith <hi>Ignatius</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Magneſians;</hi> and ſo ſay many more. Now Reaſon it ſelf muſt tell us. That when there is a Superiour Power in the one to Command, there muſt be an Obedience to anſwer in the other Party: And therefore, an Oath obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Men to that Obedience, which was ſo much their Duty before, can be no unreaſonable, or unjuſt Impoſition: But if it be unreaſonable and unjuſt, then all the Biſhops in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> are ſo too; and ſo is the Law that ſeems to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn it. <hi>Cook's Inſt. Part 4th. fol.</hi> 324. And the Rector by charging the ſaid Oath with Popery, is as ſevere a Slanderer of our Church in this point, as the moſt Rigid Fanatick, whereof himſelf is a Chip, <hi>&amp; patri ſimillima proles.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:110231:12"/>
               <p>But of all things I cannot tell how the Rector can Anſwer his declaring the uncertainty of his ever taking the ſaid Oath, though thrice benefic'd, and ſo conſequently as often oblig'd by Law to have taken it. Now, if he did not take it, then he impoſed on the Age and Eaſineſs of the Venerable Old Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Biſhop <hi>D.</hi> who Entituled him to his Rectory, and who either did, or ſhould have put this Clauſe into his Inſtitution <hi>(praeſtito primitus juramento Canonicae Obedientiae)</hi> and if this be left out, 'twas certainly through the Rector's own Craft, who was permitted to direct the Draught of his Inſtitution, and upon a Principle (as it would now ſeem) of denying, and with a deſign of refuſing any ſuch Obedience to any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. But ſays the Rector, <hi>If any ſuch Obedience be due, it muſt be in licitis &amp; honeſtis;</hi> very true, and who doubts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what has been ſaid, but that 'tis lawful and very fit for a Biſhop Adminiſtring the Sacrament in his Cathedral, to Order the Rector his Aſſiſtant, to give the Cup to two worthy Communicants in the Eſteem of all Men, but the froward Rector: And I think 'tis ſcarce a Query, whether the Rector, refuſing that juſt Command, was not forſworn, in caſe he took the Oath of Canonical Obedience; and whether he be not ſomething like it, in caſe he by a Trick avoided that Oath which <hi>de jure</hi> he ought to have taken: And whether he is not liable to the 13th Canon, <hi>Con. Aurel.</hi> 2 <hi>Clerici qui officium ſuum ad implere deſpiciunt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Loci ſui dignitate pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventur:</hi> At leaſt to that of the Canoniſt; <hi>Clericus nolens Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrare Euchariſtiam ubi &amp; quibus obligatur Arbitraria paena eſt puniendus: Aug. Bar. Cap.</hi> 17. <hi>n.</hi> 43. That is, if a Clergy-Man refuſe to Adminiſter the Sacrament where and to whom he ought, he is to be Puniſhed according to Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But, Oh, this Word <hi>(Command)</hi> is a Terrible Deſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic Word; 'tis another Rag of Popery, <hi>pag.</hi> 21.22. Now, ſince to Command in the Biſhops, and to Obey in the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, are both Rags of Popery, there muſt be a Reformation
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110231:12"/>to produce ſuch a Church, wherein no body muſt Command, and no body muſt Obey, and by my Conſent, the Rector ſhall have the Glory of this rare Invention.</p>
               <p>But to conclude the matter ſeriouſly, I bid the Rector De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to give one inſtance in any Age, where ever any Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter Aſſiſting a Biſhop in the Adminiſtration of the Lords Supper in his own Cathedral, or elſewhere, did Aſſume the confidence to repel any Communicant, <hi>invito Epiſcopo:</hi> Or did, in contradiction to the Biſhops Order, with-hold the Cup from any perſon, upon any pretence whatſoever. But ſeeing our Rector did theſe ill and irregular things, and many more, that were iniurious, both to the Biſhop and his Servants; therefore, according to his own Rule, <hi>pag.</hi> 11. He is under Obligation by the Laws of God and Man, to Acknowledg, Revoke, and make ſatisfaction for the aforeſaid Wrongs as far as he may, and to court the forgiveneſs of the injured Parties.</p>
               <p>As he is a moſt profligate Reviler of a Biſhop, Ancient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons require he ſhould beg Pardon, or be irrevocably degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Con. Carth.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 57. <hi>Clericus Maledicus maxime in Sacerdotibus cogatur ad poſtulandum veniam, ſi noluerit, degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur, nec unquam ad Officium ſine ſatisfactione revocetur.</hi> And as he is a litigious Clergy-Man, his Teſtimony ought not to be Receiv'd: <hi>Cap.</hi> 58. of the aforeſaid Canon. <hi>Clericus qui fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenter litigat, &amp; ad cauſandum facilis eſt. Teſtimonium nemo abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> grandi examine recipiat.</hi> And indeed, whoever conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Rector, as he has here been truly ſet forth, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver much regard what he ſays againſt any Man, much leſs againſt his Biſhop, who bears ſo great and clear a Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Whoſe Learning, Charity and Hoſpitality render him a worthy Prelate, and whoſe Birth and Education have made him an Accompliſh'd Gentleman.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>PAX VOBIS.</salute>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:110231:13"/>
            <head>The Printer's Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THis Anſwer had been Printed three Weeks ſooner, had not the Preſs been very much engag'd in Buſineſs that requir'd Expedition; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, 'tis not doubted but it comes ſoon enough for the <hi>Rector,</hi> who will find it no eaſie Task to clear himſelf of what is laid to his Charge, and fully to Anſwer a Book ſo well written.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:110231:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
